<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Translation on Cello&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/translation/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Translation on Cello&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/translation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Lost in Translation</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/post/lost-in-translation/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/lost-in-translation/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/post/lost-in-translation/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Lost in Translation" /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other day I picked up a phrase that still bounces around in my head from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t write in your native language, there&amp;rsquo;s always a risk that details will get lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been blogging in English so far in order to reach more people. But my mother tongue is German. Do I still manage to express what I want to convey?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think so™. But even though I think I write good English, it takes me a lot more time and energy to write a post in a foreign language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-idea&#34;&gt;The Idea
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I had the idea to try the best of both worlds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not write in my native language, where I have a deep understanding of subtle differences in meaning, idioms and vocabulary, and then simply have everything translated into the target foreign language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-test&#34;&gt;The Test
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;And in fact, what you are reading here is already the result of that experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had this text translated from German to English by deepL. It took me barely 10 minutes to write this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-question&#34;&gt;The Question
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;But does it still sound like me? Or are the little mistakes I make in my posts due to the foreign language the soul of my blog? Philosophical deep talk today&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
